So now that we understand what block
ciphers are  let's look at a classic
好了 现在我们理解了什么是分组密码 让我们来看一个经典的
example called the Data Encryption
Standard. So  just a quick reminder. Block
例子 数据加密标准DES 先快速提醒一下 分组
ciphers basically map N bits of input to N
bits of output. And we talked about two
密码基本上就是N比特输入映射到N比特输出 我们讨论两个
canonical examples  triple DES and AES. In
this segment  we're gonna talk about DES
规范的例子 三重DES和AES 这一节 我们讨论DES
and we'll talk about triple DES  actually
in the next segment. And then I also
接着在下一节讨论三重DES 我之前
mentioned before that block ciphers are
often built by iteration. In particular
提到分组密码一般是迭代构成的 特别的
we're gonna look at block ciphers that are
built by a form of iteration where a key K
我们将看到 这种分组密码的迭代方式是 一个密钥
is first expanded into a bunch of round
keys. And then a round function is applied
先扩展成一堆密钥 接着 一个轮函数
to the input message  again and again and
again. And essentially  after all these
对输入信息一次次进行作用 基本上 所有的轮函数
round functions are applied  we obtain the
resulting cipher text  okay? And again
作用后 我们就得到了密文 对吧？回过来
what we're gonna look at  how DES  the
data encryption standard  uses this
我们将要看看 DES 数据加密标准 如何使用这种
format. I just want to clear that  in
fact  to specify a block cipher of this
形式 我想澄清一点 实际上 想搞清楚这种类型的分组密码
type  one needs to specify the key
expansion mechanism  and one needs to
一是要搞清楚密钥扩展机制 一是要
specify the round function. In this segment
I'm gonna focus on the round
搞清楚轮函数 本节这里 我将集中在
function  and I'm not going to talk too much
about key expansion. But I just wanted to
轮函数 不过多地讨论密钥扩展 但是我要提一下
mention that  in fact  key expansion is
also a big part of describing how block
实际上 密钥扩展也是分组密码工作很重要的一个部分
cipher works. Okay  so let's talk about
the history of DES. Essentially  in the
好 我们来看看DES的历史 基本上 在20世纪
early 1970s  IBM realized that their
customers are demanding some special means of
七十年代早期 IBM意识到他们的顾客要求某种形式的
encryption. So they formed a Cryptography
team and the leader of that group  was
加密 所以他们组建了一个密码学团队 这团队的头儿 是
Horst Feistel  who  in the early 70s
designed a cipher called Lucifer.
Horst Feistel 他在70年代早期设计了一种密码叫Lucifer密码
Now actually it's interesting that Lucifer had a
number of variations but in fact one
事实上现在 有趣的是Lucifer密码有很多种变形 但是实际上
of the later variations had a key length that
was 128 bits and as well as a block length.
后期的一种变形 令密钥长度为128比特 分组长度也是
Okay  in 1973 the governor
realized that it's buying many commercial
好 1973年的时候官方意识到 购买了大量商业
off-the-shelf computers and so it wanted
its suppliers to actually have a good grip
现货供应的计算机 需要供货商提供一种好的
to algorithm that they could use in
products sold to the government. So in
算法能使得他们可以用卖给政府的商品 所以
1973 the National Bureau of Standards as
it was called at the time put out a
1973年 当时的国家标准局 提出一项征集令
request for proposals for a block cipher
that is going to become a federal
征集一种分组密码作为联邦
standard. And in fact IBM submitted a
variant of Lucifer. That variant actually
标准 实际上 IBM提交了一个Lucifer密码的变种
went through some modification during the
standardization process and then finally
这个变种在标准化的过程中进行了一些修正 最终
in 1976  the national bureau standard
adopted DES as a federal standard. And  in
在1976年 国家标准局接受DES作为联邦标准 而且 实际上
fact  for DES it's interesting that the
key length was far reduced from Lucifer.
对DES来说 有趣的是它的密钥长度比Lucifer密码短得多
It's only 56 bits. And the block length
was also reduced to 64 bits. And in
只有56比特 分组长度也减少到64比特 事实
fact  these decisions  especially the
decision to reduce the key length  is
这些决定 尤其是缩短密钥长度的决定
going to be a key length limit of DES and
was a source of many complaints over the whole
成为DES密钥长度的一个限制 关于这个在整个DES的使用过程中
process of using. In particular  already
back in 1997 DES was broken by exhaustive search
不断遭人诟病 尤其 在1997年 DES遭受穷举搜索攻击
meaning that a machine was able to search
through all two to the 56 possible keys to
意味着一台机器可以搜素所有的2的56次方个密钥
recover a particular challenge key. And in
fact we're going to talk about exhaustive
从而恢复出特定挑战密钥 我们也会在后面讨论
search quite a bit. It's quite an
interesting question  and there are
一下穷举搜索攻击 那是个非常有意思的问题 但是
various ways to defend against exhaustive
search. And basically the experiment in 1997
抵抗穷举搜索攻击的方法有很多 基本上 1997年的这次实验
kinda spelled the doom of DES. It meant
that DES itself  is no longer secure.
注定了DES的命数 也就是说 DES本身不再安全
As a result  the National Institute of
Standards  as it became known  issued a
因此 现在的国家标准研究所 发布了新的
request for proposals. For our next
generation's block cipher standard and in
项目征集 我们下一代的分组密码标准
2000 it standardized on a cipher called Rijndael.
Which became the advanced encryption
在2000年确定为Rijindael密码 它最终成为高级加密
standard  AES. And we'll talk about AES
later on. But in this segment  I wanna
标准 AES 后面我们会讨论AES 但是在这一节 我想
describe how DES works. Now  DES is a
cipher  it's an amazingly successful
描述一下DES是怎么工作的 现在 DES是一种有着惊人成就的
cipher. It's been used in the banking
industry. In fact  there's a classic
密码 在银行业也广为采用 实际上 有一种经典的
network called the Electronic
Clearinghouse  which banks use to clear
网络 称为电子清算所 借助这个银行互相之间
checks with one another. And DES is used
for integrity in those transactions. It's
清算支票 DES被用来保证这些交易的完整性
also used in commerce. In fact  it was
very popular up to date  as the
商业上也用这个 实际上 截止最近 它还非常流行 在网络
main encryption mechanism for the web. Of
course  now  that's been replaced by AES
上还是主要的加密机制 当然 现在 已经逐渐被AES
and other ciphers. Overall  it's a
very successful cipher in terms of
和其它密码代替 总的来说 在应用上DES是一个非常成功的
deployment. DES also has a very rich
history of attacks  which we'll talk about
密码 对DES的攻击也是由来已久 我们将在下一节讨论
at next segment. Okay  so now  let's
talking about the construction of DES. So
好 现在 让我们看看DES的结构
the core idea behind DES is what called
a Feistel network  named in Horst Feistel.
DES的核心理念是Feistel网络 得名自Horst Feistel
And basically  it's a very clever idea for
building the block cipher out of arbitrary
基本上 Feistel网络是一个非常聪明的方法 利用任意f1到fd的函数
functions  F1 to FD. Okay now imagine we
have these functions F1 to FD
构造分组密码 好 现在想象我们有这些函数f1到fd
that happens to match n bits to n bits.
Now these are arbitrary functions
从n比特映射到n比特 这些是任意函数
they don't have to be invertible or
anything. What we gonna do
不需要不可逆或者其它条件 我们现在想做的是
is building aninvertible function
out of those D functions by
用d个函数构造一个可逆函数 通过构造
building a new function we'll call capital
F that maps 2n bits to 2n bits.
一个新的函数 用大写F来表示 将2n比特映射到2n比特
And the construction is described right
here. So here we have our inputs. You
这里描述了这个构造 所以 这里我们有输入 你会注意到
notice  there are two blocks of n bits.
In other words  the input is actually
这有两组n比特数据 换句话说 输入实际上就是
2n bits. The R and L stand for right and
left. Typically  people describe a
2n比特 R和L分别代表右边和左边 通常 人们描述
Feistel network from top to bottom. In
that case  these n bits really would be
Feistel网络都是从上到下 那样 这n比特分别为左边和右边
right and left. But here it is more
convenient for me to describe it
但是这里为了方便我描述 我横着来
horizontally. So if we follow the R
inputs. You realize it basically gets
现在我们看看R这边的输入 你看它就是
copied into the L output  without any
change at all. Okay? However  the L
L这边的输出 没有任何变化 对吧？但是L
inputs  is changed somewhat. What
happens is  the R inputs is fit into
这边的输入 发生变化了 变化就是 R这边的
the function F1 and the result is then
XORed with L0 and that becomes the new R1
输入经过一个函数变化f1的结果和L0进行异或 结果是新的R1
input. Okay  so this is called one round
of a Feistel network  and is done using
输入 好 这个就是Feistel网络的一轮
the function F1. Now we do this again with
another round of the Feistel network
这里用到了一个f1函数 现在我们再看下一轮Feistel网络
with the function F2  and we do it again
and again and again  utill we get to the
这里用到了f2 然后我们一遍遍地这样做 直到我们
last round  and we do it again with the
function FD. And finally  the output is
到最后一轮 用函数fd 最后输出
Rd Ld. Okay. So  if you like  we can write
this in symbols. That basically  Li is
是Rd和Ld.好 如你所愿 我们用符号把它写出来
simply equal to Ri-1. And Ri
let's see  that's the more complicated
Li=Ri-1 Ri 要更复杂一些 我们看看
one. Ri is equal  well  let's just follow
the lines here. Ri is just equal to Fi
就跟着这线条这里 Ri=Fi（Ri-1）异或Li-1（这里应该是bug不能是Li）
applied to  Ri-1 XOR Li. Okay?
So this  and this is basically  i goes
对吧？所以这个我基本上就是从
from  1 to d. So this is the equation
that defines a Feistel network  mapping a
1走到d 所以这就是定义Feistel网络的方程 把2n
2n bit inputs to 2n bit outputs. So
here we have the  again  I just copied the
比特的输入映射到2n比特的输出 所以这边我们还有 就是把
picture of the Feistel network. And the
amazing claim is that  in fact  it doesn't
Feistel网络的图复制一下 这里比较奇特的是 实际上
matter what functions you give me. For
any functions  F1 to FD that you give me
不管你给我什么函数 对于任何函数 f1到fd
the resulting Feistel network function is
in fact  invertible. And the way we're
Feistel网络函数 实际上是可逆的 我们证明
going to prove that is basically we're
going to construct an inverse  because not
这一点的方法 基本上就是我们要构造一个逆 因为不仅它可逆
only is it invertible  it's efficiently
invertible. So let's see. Look at
而且它的逆很容易计算 所以我们看一下 我们看
one round of a Feistel network  so
here  this is the inputs  Ri Li  and this
Feistel网络的一轮 这里 这个是输入 Ri和Li 这里是输出
is the output Ri+1  Li+1. And now what I'm
going to ask you is to invert this.
Ri+1和Li+1 现在我想让你求逆
So let's see. Suppose now the input that
we're given is Ri+1  Li+1 and we want to
所以 我们看 假设现在给的输入是Ri+1和Li+1 我们想计算
compute Ri Li. So we want to compute the
round in the reverse direction. So let's
Ri和Li 也就是我们想反方向计算这一轮 看一下我们咋做
see if we can do it. Well  let's look at
Ri. So  Ri is very easy. Basically  Ri is
Ri Ri很简单 其实
just equal to Li+1. So Li+1 just becomes
Ri. But now  let me ask you  to write the
Ri=Li+1 所以 Li+1变成Ri 现在 我问你了 如何用
expression for Li in terms of Ri+1  and Li+1.
Ri+1和Li+1写出Li的表达式
So I hope everybody sees that  basically  Li+1
is fed into the function Fi+1.
我希望每个人都知道 Li+1输入函数fi+1的结果和
The result is XORed with Ri+1
and that gives the Li input.
Ri+1进行异或 就得到Li
So this the inverse of one round
of a Feistel network.
所以 这是Feistel网络一轮的逆
And if we draw this as a diagram  let's just
write the picture for the inverse.
如果我们画个图 让我们看看逆的图
So here you notice the input is Ri+1  Li+1
and the output is Ri Li. Right?
这里你看到输入是Ri+1和Li+1 输出是Ri和Li 对吧？
So we're computing  we're inverting  the
rounds. So you notice that the inverse of
我们这样这一轮就算出来了 求逆了 你应该注意到
a Feistel round looks pretty much the
same as the Feistel round in the
Feistel的一轮的逆和正向的一轮基本一样
forward direction. Literally see  you
know  just for a technical reason  it's
字面上来看 你知道 因为技术原因
kinda the mirror image of one another. But
it's basically  the same construct. And
实际上这互为镜像 但是 它们就是一样的构造
when we put these inverted rounds back
together. We essentially get the inverse
如果我们把每一轮的逆都放到一起 我们就得到了整个
of the entire Feistel network. So you
notice we start off with the round number D
Feistel网络的逆 注意 我们这里从第d轮
with the inverse of round number D
then we do the inverse of round number D-1
开始算d轮的逆 接着做第d-1轮
and so on and so forth until we
get to the inverse of the first round. And
这么一直做下去 直到第一轮
we get our final outputs which is R0  L0
like this is the inputs and we manage to
最后我们得到输出是R0和L0 就像这样 已知
invert basically Rd  Ld and get R0  L0
and the interesting thing is that
Rd和Ld 得到R0和L0 有趣的是
these inversion circuits look
pretty much the same as the encryption
这个逆网络和加密网络
circuits and the only difference is that
the functions are applied in reverse order.
看起来基本是一样的 唯一不同的是这些作用函数的顺序是相反的
Right here we started with Fd and ended with
F1. Whereas when we were encrypting  we
就是我们这里从fd开始到f1结束 而在加密的时候
started with F1 and ended with Fd. So  for
hardware designers  this is very
从f1开始到fd结束 所以 对硬件设计师而言 这个很有
attractive  because  basically  if you
wanna save hardware  you realize that your
吸引力 因为 基本上 你可以节省硬件
encryption hardware is identical to your
decryption hardware. So you only have to
你会发现 你得加密硬件和解密硬件一样 所以你只需要实现
implement one algorithm  and you get both
algorithms the same way. The only
一个算法 那这两个算法你就都实现了 唯一的
difference is that the functions are
applied in reverse order. Okay. So this
区别就是这些函数是逆序的 好
Feistel mechanism is a general method
for building invertible functions from
这种Feistel机制作为一种基本方法利用任何函数f1到fd
arbitrary functions F1 to Fd and in fact
it's used in many different block ciphers.
构造可逆函数 在多种分组密码中广泛使用
Although  interestingly  it's not actually
used in AES. So  there are many other
但是有趣的是在AES中没有用 所以
block ciphers that use a Feistel
network. Or  of course  they differ from
Feistel网络在很多分组密码中都有 当然 因为f1到fd的不同
DES in the functions F1 to Fd. But AES
actually uses a completely different type
它们和DES不尽相同 但是AES用的是完全不同的一种
of structure that's actually not a
Feistel network. We'll see how AES
结构 不是Feistel网络 我们后面几节课
works in a couple of segments. So now that
we know what Feistel networks are  let
会研究AES是怎么工作的 所以现在我们知道Feistel网络了 我们
me mention an important theorem about the
theory of Feistel networks that shows
看一个重要的关于Feistel网络理论的定理 这个定理
why they're a good idea. This theorem is
due to Luby and Rackoff back in 1985  and it
也证明了它是一个好方法 定理是1985年Luby和Rackoff提出的
says the following. Suppose I have a
function that is a secure pseudorandom
描述如下 假设我有一个函数 伪随机
function  okay. So it's indistinguishable
from random and happens to act on N bits.
函数 它和随机函数不可区分 从n比特输入映射到
So it maps N bits to N bits and uses a
key K. Then  it turns out  that if you use
nbite输出 在密钥k的作用下 这样 结果是如果你
this function in three rounds of a Feistel
network. What you end up with is a secure
用这个函数进行三轮Feistel变化 你将得到一个
pseudo random permutation. In other words
what you end up with is an invertible
安全的伪随机置换 换句话说 你得到了一个可逆的函数
function that is indistinguishable from a
truly random invertible function. And I
这个可逆函数和随机可逆函数不可区分 我
hope you remember that the true definition
of a secure block cipher is that it needs
希望你记得安全分组密码的定义是 需要它是一个
to be a secure pseudo random permutation.
So what this theorem says  is that if you
安全的伪随机置换 所以 这个定理说的是 如果你用
start with a secure pseudo random
function  you end up with a secure block
一个安全的伪随机函数 那么你就能得到一个安全的分组
cipher. Basically  that's what this is.
And let me explain in a little bit more
密码 好 就是这样 让我多解释一下
detail what's actually going on here. So
essentially  the PRF is used in every
这是怎么回事 基本上 PRF在
round of the Feistel network. So  in
other words  here  what's actually
Feistel网络的每一轮都用 所以 换句话说 这里
computed is the PRF using one secret key
K0. Here  what's computed is the PRF
算的就是PRF在密钥K0作用下 这里算的是
using a different secret key  of course
applied to R1. And here we have yet
在密钥K1作用下R1的函数值 这里是另一个密钥K2
another secret key  K1 applied  K2 applied
to R2. And you notice  this is why
作用于R2 这你就会发现 为什么
basically this Feistel construction
uses keys in K cubed. In other words  it
这个Feistel结构的密钥空间是K的三次方 换句话说 它用了
uses three independent keys. So it's very
important that the keys are actually
3个独立的密钥 这里 密钥互相独立 十分重要
independent. So really  we need three
independent keys. And then we end up with
也就是说 我们需要真正独立的三个密钥 这样我们就得到了
a secure pseudorandom permutation. Okay
so that's the theory behind Feistel
一个安全的伪随机置换 好 这就是Feistel网络背后的理论
networks. And now that we understand that
we can actually look at the specifics of DES.
先在 我们明白了这个 我们可以看看具体DES的情况
So DES is basically a sixteen round
Feistel network  okay. So there are
DES实际上是一个16轮的Feistel网络 好 这是函数
functions F1 to F16 that map 32 bits to
32 bits  and as a result  the DES itself
f1到f16将32比特映射32比特 所以 DES
acts on 64 bit blocks  2x32. Now the
sixteen round functions in DES are
是作用在64比特的分组上 就是2*32.现在 DES的16个轮函数
actually all derived from a single
function F. Just used with different keys.
实际上是从一个函数F来的 就是用的不同的密钥
So in fact  these are the different round
keys. So Ki is  a round key. And it's
所以 轮密钥不同 ki是一个轮密钥 它是
basically derived from the key K which derived
from the 56 bit DES key K. Okay and I'll
从密钥K得出的 长度为56比特的DES密钥K 好 我马上
describe what this function F is in just a
minute. But basically that  you see that
来说一下这个函数F 但是实际上 你看到使用
by using sixteen different round keys  we
get sixteen different round functions. And
16个不同的轮密钥 我们得到16个不同的轮函数
that gives us the Feistel network. So just
on a high level how the DES works
从而得到Feistel网络 这就是从上层看DES是怎么工作的
basically you have a 64 bit input. The
first thing it does is  this initial
基本上你有一个64比特的输入 首先 这个初始置换
permutation that just permutes the 64 bits
around. Namely it maps bit number one to
仅仅置换一下这64比特的位置 即把第一个比特置换到
bit number six. Bit number two to bit
number seventeen  and so on. This is not
第六个比特 第二个比特置换到第17个比特这样 这不是为了安全
for security reasons  this is just
specified in the standard. Then we go into
就是标准里有这一条（实际上是为了打乱语言统计特性）
the sixteen round Feistel network. That
actually  you now know how it works.
接着 进入到16轮Feistel网络 你知道它是怎么工作的
Basically uses the function F1 to F16  as
specified before. And then  we
就是使用我们前面说过的f1到f16函数 接着
have another permutation  it's called the
final permutation. That's just the inverse
有另外一个置换 称为最终置换 其实就是初始置换
of the initial permutation. Again
it just permutes bits around  this is not
的逆 也是置换位置 对安全性没什么
necessary for security reasons. And then
we finally get  the final outputs. Okay.
贡献 最终我们得到输出 好
Now  as we said  there's a key expansion
step  which I'm not gonna describe. But
现在 像我们前面说的 有一个密钥扩展的步骤 我就不描述了
basically  this 56-bit DES key is expanded
into these rounds keys. Where each round
但是 这56比特的DES密钥扩展出这些轮密钥 轮密钥是
key  is 48 bits. Okay  so we have sixteen
48 bit round keys  and they're basically
48比特的 好 我们有16个48比特的轮密钥
used in the sixteen rounds of DES. And
then when you want to invert the cipher
它们用于DES的16个轮 接下来 你要想一下怎么对这个密码求逆
all you do is you use these  round keys
these sixteen round keys  in reverse
你所要做的就是用这些轮密钥 这16个轮密钥 逆序
order. Okay  so now that we understand the
DES structure  the only thing that's left
好 现在我们明白DES的结构了 剩下唯一的问题就是解释
to do is specify the function  capital F.
So let me explain how this function works.
这个函数 大F 我来解释一下这个函数是怎么工作的
So basically  it takes  as inputs  its  32
bit value  let's call it X. But in
基本上 它有32比特的输入 写作X
reality  you remember  this is R0
R1  R-2  R3  so on and so
实际上 你得记得 这就是R0R1R3等等
forth. These are 32 bit values. And then
it takes  also  a 48 bit round key. So
这是32比特 它用了一个48比特的轮密钥
here we have our key Ki  which happens to
be 48 bits. The first thing it does  is it
所以这里有密钥ki 它是48比特 首先
goes through an expansion box. And this
expansion box basically take thirty two
经过一个扩展盒 这个扩展盒是把32比特映射成
bits  and maps them into 48 bits. Now  all
the expansion box does is just replicates
48比特 现在 扩展盒就是重复其中
some bits  and move other bits around. So
for example  bit #1 of X is replicated
的一些比特 把其它比特移动一下 例如 X的1号比特在
into positions 2 and 48 in the output.
Bit #2 of X is positioned in as bit
位置2和48 X的2号比特被放在
#3 of the output. And so on and so
forth  just by replicating some of the
3号位置作为输出 就这样 重复X的某些比特
bits of X  we expand the input into 48
bits. The next thing we do is we compute
我们把这32比特扩展成48比特 下一步我们把这48比特
an XOR with the round key.
Sometimes people say that cryptographers
和轮密钥异或 有些人说密码学家就是算
only compute XORs. This is an example of
that  where  well  we just do XORs in this
异或 呵呵 这就是个例子 好 我们就在这个做异或
function. And then comes the magic of DES
where  actually  these 48 bits are broken
下面就是DES的神奇之处了 这里 这48比特分成
into eight groups of six bits. Six  seven
eight. And so let me draw  and then what
8组 每组6比特 6 7 8 让我在这儿画一下
happens is  so yes. Each one
of these wires is  six bits. And
好 自然的 这里这些 是6比特 接着
then  they go into what  are called
S boxes. And I'll explain S boxes
他们进入到所谓的S盒 我马上就会讲到
in just a minute. The S boxes are kind of
the smarts of  DES. And then  the S
S盒 S盒实际上是DES的核心 S盒
box is basically a map  six bits to four
bits. So  the outputs of the S boxes are
实际上是一个映射 把6比特映射到4比特 所以S盒输出是
these four bits. They're collected. This
gives up 32 bits  right? Eight groups of
这四个比特 把它们合起来 就给出32比特 对吧？8个
four bits  gives us 32 bits and then
finally this is fed into yet another
4比特 给我们32比特 最终 输入到另一个
permutation which just maps the bits
around. So  for example bit number one
置换中 这个置换就是换一下位置 例如第一个比特
will go to bit number nine  bit number two
will go to bit number fifteen and so on.
跑到第9个的位置 第二个比特跑到第15个的位置 等等
So it just permutes the 32 bits around and
that's the final 32 bit output of this F function.
它仅仅就是置换这32个比特 这是F函数最终的32比特输出
Okay? So by using different
round keys  essentially  we get different
好吧？所以 使用不同的轮密钥 基本上 我们得到不同
round functions  and that's how we form
the sixteen round functions of DES. Now
的轮函数 这样构成DES的16个轮函数
the only thing that  left to specify are
these S boxes. So the S boxes  literally
现在 剩下的唯一问题就是解释这个S盒 S盒 字面上讲
are just functions from six bits to four
bits. They are just implemented as a look
就是一个从6比特到4比特的函数 就像用一个查找
up table. Right? So describing a function
from six bits to four bits basically
表一样 对吧？描述一个从6比特到4比特的函数基本上就是
amounts to writing the output of the
function on all two to the six possible inputs.
写一个输入为2的6次方的函数的输出
Two to the six is 64. So we just
have a table that literally contains 64 values.
2的6次方是64 所以我们需要一个有64个值的表
Where each value is four bits. So
here is an example  this happens to be the
每个值是4比特 举个例子 这个是第五个S盒
fifth S box  and you see that this is a
table that contains 64 values right?
你看 这是一个含64个值的表吧？
It's four by sixteen. So  64 values. For
example  if you wanna look at  the output
4乘以16 所以64个值 例如 你想找输出
that corresponds to 0-1-1-0-1-1. Okay  then
you look at these two bits. This is 01
对应011011的输出 好 你看一下这两个比特 01
and these four bits are 1101  and you see
that the output is 1001. The four bits
这4个比特1101 你看到输出是1001.
output 1001. Okay  so the S boxes are just
implemented as these tables.
输出的四个比特是1001.好 S盒就是用这些个表
Now the question is  how are these S boxes chosen.
How are these tables actually chosen by
现在问题是 这些S盒是怎么选的 设计者是怎么选的
the designers of this. So to give you some
intuitions for that  lets start with a
为了让你更清楚些 我们先给个S盒
very bad choice for S boxes. So imagine
the S boxes were linear. What do I mean by
失败的例子 想象S盒是线性的 什么意思？
that? I mean that imagine that these six
bit inputs literally were just
就是想象这6比特的输入
XORed with one another in different
ways to produce the four bit outputs.
用不同的方式互相异或得到4比特输出
Okay  another way of writing that is that
we can write the S box as a matrix vector product.
好 另一种写法是我们可以把S盒写成一个矩阵向量积
So here you have the matrix Ai.
And the vector  the six bit vector X.
所以这里 你有矩阵Ai 和向量 6比特向量的向量X
And you can see that  if we write this matrix
vector product  basically  we take the
你可以看到 如果写这个矩阵向量积 就是用
inner product of this vector with the
input vector. Remember  these are all bits.
这个向量和输入向量的内积作为输出 记住 这都是比特
So the six bits vector inner
product. Another six bit vector  and we do
所以 6比特的向量内积 另外6比特向量 进行
that modulo two  you realize  basically
what we're computing is X2 XOR X3.
模2加 你看到了 我们计算的就是X2异或X3.
Right? Because only position two and
position three have 1's in it.
对吧 因为只有位置2和位置3有1
And similarly the next  inner product will
produce X1 XOR X4 XOR X5 and so on and
下面 类似的 这个内积是X1异或X4异或X5 下面类似
so forth. Okay. So you can literally see
that if the S boxes are implemented this
好 你可以看到这个S盒是这么操作的
way. Then  all they do  is just apply the
matrix A to the input vector X. Which is
那么 就是对输入向量X进行矩阵A的一个矩阵变换
why we say  that in this case the S boxes
are completely linear. Now  I claimed that
这就是我们说的S盒是完全线性的 现在我要说
in fact that if the S boxes were linear  then DES
would be totally insecure. The reason is
如果S盒是线性的 那么DES就是完全不安全的 原因是
if the S boxes are linear  then all that
DES does is just compute XOR of various
如果S盒是线性的 那么所有DES做的运算就是异或啊 各种置换之流
things and permute and shuffle bits
around. So it's just XORs and bit
所以 DES就是异或和比特
permutations  which means that as a
result  all of DES is just a linear
置换 这意味着 DES就是个
function. In other words  there will be a
Matrix B. Of these dimensions. Basically
线性函数 换句话说 会有一个矩阵B 这么多维的
it's a matrix B that has width 832.
Basically what I will do is I will write
实际上 这个矩阵是832维的 就是64
the 64 bit message plus the sixteen round
keys as one long vector. Alright  so the
比特消息中的64加16轮密钥中的16 所以消息是64比特
message is 64 bits and there are sixteen
round keys. Each one is 48 and that  if
密钥是16.每一个是48 如果你算一下 64+16*48=832
you do the math  it's basically 832. Okay?
So I write these values  the keys and the
就是832.这里我写下来 这些值 密钥和
message  as one long vector and then there
will be this matrix that essentially when
消息 作为一个长向量 这里有这个矩阵 你计算这个矩阵
you compute these matrix vector products.
Essentially you get the different bits of
向量积就行了 这样 你得到密文的不同比特 所以
the ciphertext. So there's 64 of these
rows and as a result  you get 64 bits of
这里有64行 所以 你得到64比特的密文
ciphertext. Okay  so this is what it
means for DES to be linear. So if you
好 这是说DES是线性的 所以 如果你稍微思考一下这个
think a little bit about this  you realize
that the S boxes are the only nonlinear
你就会意识到S盒是DES里唯一的非线性部件
part of DES. So if the S boxes were
linear  then the entire circuit is linear
所以 如果S盒也是线性的 那整个结构就是线性的
and therefore can be expressed as this
matrix. Now if that's the case then DES
因此 可以用这个矩阵来表示 如果是这种情况 那么DES是一
would be terrible as a secure pseudorandom
permutation. And let me give you a very
个糟糕的安全的伪随机置换 让我给你看个很简单的例子
simple example. Basically if you did the
XOR of three outputs of DES  well
如果你对DES的三个输出做异或 想一下这是
let's think what that means. Basically we
would be looking at B times  the matrix B
什么意思 基本上我们会看到B乘以 这个定义DES
that defines DES  times  one vector
XOR B times another vector
的矩阵B 乘以一个向量 异或上B乘以另外一个向量
XOR B times a third vector. We
could take the B out of the parentheses so
再异或B乘以第三个向量 我们把B提出来 这样
we'd be basically doing B times this
vector over here. But of course K XOR K XOR K
得到B乘以这个向量 但是显然k异或k再异或k
this is just K. And so if you
think about what that means  basically we
就是k 所以 你想一下 我们就得到
just got back DES of K at the point M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. But this means that now DES
以密钥k加密的m1异或m2异或m3的DES密文 但是这意味着DED
has this horrible relation. That can be
tested. Right? So  basically  if you
有这个可怕的相关关系 我可一检测一下 是吧？所以 本质上 如果你
XOR the output of three values
M1  M2  M3  you'll get the value of
异或这三个值的输出 m1 m2和m3 你会得到
DES  at the point M1 XOR M2 XOR M3. Now this
is not a relation that is going to hold
这三个值异或的DES加密结果 这个性质导致DES这个函数
for a random function. A random function
is not going to satisfy this equality.
不能作为随机函数 一个随机函数不能满足这样的条件
And so you get a very easy test to tell you
that DES is not a random function.
所以 你有一种很简单的方法告诉你DES不是一个随机函数
In fact  maybe you can take that as a small
exercise. It's not even difficult to see
实际上 我们可能会以此做个简单的练习（作业里有） 甚至不难发现
that given enough input output pairs  you
can literally recover the entire secret key.
有足够的输入输出对 你可以恢复出整个密钥
Yeah. You just need 832 input output
pairs  and you'll be able recover the
是的！你只需要832对输入输出 你就能恢复出
entire secret key. And so if the S boxes
were linear  DES would be completely
整个密钥 所以 如果S盒是线性的 DES将彻底
insecure. It turns out  actually  even if
the S boxes were close to being linear. In
不安全 事实表明 实际上 即便S盒是近似线性的 换句话说
other words  the S boxes were linear most
of the time. So maybe for 60 out of the 64
S盒在大多数时候是线性的 可能对64个输入有60个输出是线性的
inputs  the S boxes were linear. It turns
out that would also be enough to break
S就是线性的了 这样我们也能攻破DES
DES  and we're gonna see why later on. In
particular  if you choose the S boxes at
我们后面会研究一下为什么 特别的 如果你随机选择了S盒
random  it turns out they'll tend to be
somewhat close to linear functions. As a
你会发现它们都多少趋于线性函数
result  you'll be able to totally break
DES. You'll just be able to recover the
结果就是 你能彻底攻破DES 你能在
key  in basically  very little time. And
so  the designers of DES actually
很短的时间内获得密钥 DES的设计者
specified a number of rules they use for
choosing the S boxes. And it's not
给出了一系列选择S盒的规则 不出意料的
surprising  the first rule is that these
functions are far away from being linear.
第一规则就是这些函数不能是线性的
Okay. So  in other words  there is no
function that agrees with a large fraction
好 换句话说 就是没有（线性）函数能满足大部分S盒的输出
of the outputs of the S box. And then
there are all these other rules  for
还有一起其它的规则 比如
example  there are exactly four to one
maps  right? So  every output has exactly
S盒是个4对1的映射 就是说每个输出对应四个
four pre-images and so on and so forth. So
we understand now why they chose the S
原像 等等还有其它 现在在我们理解了为什么S盒要有这样的
boxes they way they did and in fact its
all done to defeat certain attacks on DES.
选择方式 实际上都是为了抵抗某种对DES的攻击
Okay. So that's the end of the
description of DES  and in the next few
好 我们对DES就讲到这里 下几节
segments we are going to look at the
security of DES.
我们将看一下DES的安全性